伦敦　1593年
伊利莎白式剧场全盛时期
两家剧场互相争抢编剧和观众
在城北的是卡登剧场
英国最红巨星理查·波贝的老本营
过了河则是由对头菲立浦汉斯乐
一个金钱周转有麻烦的商人
…所建的玫瑰剧场…
Henslowe, do you know what happens to a man who doesn't pay his debts?
汉斯乐，你知道欠钱不还会有什么后果吗？
是悲剧，债主复仇记
His boots catch fire!
他的靴子会着火
Why do you how!...when it is I who am bitten?
你干嘛哀嚎？我才是受害人
- What am I, Mr. Lambert? - Bitten, Mr. Fennyman.
蓝伯特，我怎么啦？－被诈了，费尼门先生
How badly bitten, Mr. Frees?
诈了多少钱，佛利先生？
Twelve pounds, one schilling and fourpence, Mr. Fennyman, including interest.
十二镑，一先令和四便士，包括利息
- Aaah! I can pay you! - When?
我还你!－什么时候？
Two weeks! Three weeks at the most! Oh, for pity's sake!
两个礼拜！最多三个礼拜！饶了我吧！
Take them out.
把他脚抬起来
Where will you find...
你去那里找…
Sixteen pounds, five schillings and ninepence.
十六镑，五先令和九便士
Including interest, in three weeks?
…包括利息？
- I have a wonderful new play. - Put them back in.
我有个绝佳的新剧本 - 把他脚放回去
- It's a comedy! - Cut off his nose.
是个喜剧！－割掉他鼻子
It's a new comedy by William Shakespeare.
是威廉·莎士比亚的喜剧
- And his ears. - And a share!
耳朵也割掉
We will be partners, Mr. Fennyman!
你也有份！我们合伙！
Partners?
合伙？
It's a crowd-tickler.
一定受欢迎
Mistaken identities. Shipwreck. Pirate king.
阴差阳错啦，海难啦，盗王等
- A bit with a dog, and love triumphant. - I think I've seen it.
还有狗和恋爱之类的 - 太俗套
I didn't like it.
我不喜欢
- But this time it is by Shakespeare. - What's it called?
但这次是莎士比亚写的 - 叫什么？
Romeo and Ethel, the Pirate's Daughter.
罗密欧与爱索，海盗之女
Good title.
名字不错
A play takes time. Find the actors, rehearsals.
上演一部戏很花时间，得找演员，排演
Let's say we open in two weeks.
我们两个礼拜就上演
That's, what, 500 groundlings at tuppence a head.
500个站位一个人两便士
In addition, 400 backsides at threepence, a penny extra for cushions.
400个坐位一个人三便士，再加一便士有坐垫
Call it, uh, 200 cushions.
假如卖出200个坐垫
Say two performances for safety. How much is that, Mr. Frees?
保守点就算两场，有多少收入？
- Twenty pounds to the penny, Mr. Fennyman. - Correct.
整整二十磅－对
- But I have to pay the actors and the author. - Share of the profits.
我得付演员和作者- 大家来分利润
There's never any - Of course not.
根本就没利润- 当然没有
Oh-- Oh, Mr. Fennyman, I think you might have hit upon something.
费尼门先生，你出了个好主意
Sign there.
在那里签名
So, Romeo and Ethel, the Pirate's Daughter.
罗密欧与爱索，海盗之女
Almost finished?
快写完了？
Oh, without doubt he's completing it at this very moment.
毫无疑问，马上就写完了
<font size=35><b>【恋爱中的莎士比亚】</b></font>
阿文河畔的斯特拉福
Will. Will!
威廉
Where is my play?
剧本呢？
Tell me you have it nearly done. Tell me you have it started.
告诉我你快写完了，告诉我你已经开始写了
Doubt that the stars are fire, doubt that the sun doth move.
“怀疑星星不是火，怀疑太阳会转动。”
No, no, we haven't the time. Talk prose.
没时间了，别再做诗了
Where is my play?
我的剧本呢？
- It is all locked safe in here. - God be praised.
全都安全的锁在这儿了 - 赞美主
Locked?
在那？
- As soon as I find my muse. - Who is she this time?
只要我一找到灵感 - 这次是哪个女人？
She is always Aphrodite.
还是阿佛黛
Aphrodite Baggot, who does it behind the Dog and Trumpet?
阿佛黛，老在酒吧后头搞的那个？
Henslowe, you have no soul,
汉斯乐，你没灵魂
so how can you understand the emptiness that seeks a soul mate?
你怎能了解渴求灵魂伙伴时的空虚？
Ow! Will!
威廉
I am a dead man, and buggered to boot.
我被搞得好惨，死定了
My theater is closed by the plague these twelve weeks.
我的剧院因为瘟疫关了十二个礼拜
My actors are forced to tour the inn yards of England...
我的演员被迫流落到酒馆去表演…
while Mr. Burbage and the Chamberlain's Men are invited to court...
而波贝和张伯伦的演员却受邀到皇宫…
and receive ten pounds to play your piece,
演你的戏得了十镑的奖赏
written for my theater, by my writer, at my risk...
用写给我剧场的剧本，我的编剧，我自己冒险…
when you were green and grateful.
用你这种年轻没经验的人
What piece? Richard Crookback? - No! It's comedy they want.
那出戏？理查三世？- 不！他们要喜剧
Like Romeo and Ethel.
像罗密欧与爱索
- Who wrote that? - Nobody. You were writing it for me.
谁写的？- 还没开始。你得替我写
- I gave you three pound a month since. - Half what you owe me.
我一个月前就给你三镑 - 只值你欠我的一半
I'm still due for One Gentleman of Verona.
你还得付我威洛纳之绅的钱
What is money to you and me? l, your patron, you, my wordwright.
钱对你我有何意义？我出资，你编剧
When the plague lifts,
等瘟疫过去
Burbage will have a new play by Christopher Marlowe for the Curtain.
波贝会有克里斯多夫·马罗替卡登剧场写的新戏
- I will have nothing for the Rose. - Mr. Henslowe.
玫瑰剧场却没戏
- Will you lend me 50 pounds? - Fifty pounds?
借我五十镑?- 五十镑？
- What for? - Burbage offers me a partnership in the Chamberlain's Men.
波贝要我成为张伯伦剧组的合伙人
For 50 pounds, my days as a hired player are over.
只要五十镑，我受雇演员的生涯就结束了
Oh, cut out my heart. Throw my liver to the dogs.
哦　我心淌血　你真可怜
No, then?
你意思是不肯罗？
Theaters are handmaidens of the devil!
剧场是魔鬼之仆！
The players breed lewdness in your wives and wickedness in your children!
演员和你的老婆厮混，教坏你的小孩！
And the Rose smells thusly rank by any name!
管你叫什么玫瑰剧场，闻起来都一样臭！
I say, a plague on both their houses!
我咒他们全因瘟疫而关门！
Where are you going?
你要去哪里？
My weekly confession.
我的每周告解
药剂师、炼丹师、占星师
Words, words, words.
文思，文思，文思
Once, I had the gift.
我曾有此天赋
I could make love out of words as a potter makes cups of clay.
我能用文思创造出爱情，就像泥匠用泥块雕塑出杯子
Love that overthrows empires.
爱能推翻帝国
Love that binds two hearts together, come hellfire and brimstone.
爱让两颗心结合，冒出熊熊烈火
For sixpence a line, I could cause a riot in a nunnery.
一行台词付我六便士，我能在修道院引起骚动
But now- -And yet you tell me you lie with women.
但现在…- 可是你告诉我你骗女人上床
Black Sue, Fat Phoebe,
黑女人苏，胖菲比
Rosaline, Burbage's seamstress, Aphrodite, who does it behind--
洛丝琳，波贝的缝衣妇，阿佛黛，那个在酒吧后
Yes, now and again. What of it?
偶而罢了,又怎样呢？
I have lost my gift.
我已失去了天赋
I am here to help you.
我能帮你忙
Tell me, in your own words.
用你自己的话告诉我
I-lt's as if my quill is broken,
就好像我的羽毛笔断了
as if the organ of my imagination has dried up,
好像我想像力枯竭了
as if the proud tower of my genius has collapsed.
好像我天才之塔倒塌了
- Interesting. - Nothing comes.
有趣－全没了
Most interesting.
很有趣
It's like trying to pick a lock with a wet herring.
好像想要用湿鲱鱼当钥匙开门
Tell me, are you lately humbled in the act of love?
你最近的性生活是否不如意？
How long has it been?
多久了？
A goodly length in times past, but lately--
相当久了，但最近…
No, no. You have a wife, children?
不，不。你有老婆，小孩？
Aye.
有
I was a lad of 18.
当年我才18岁
Anne Hathaway was a woman half as old again.
安海乐薇比我大九岁
- A woman of property? - She had a cottage.
这女人有财产?－她有一栋小屋
One day she was three months gone with child, so-- - And your relations?
她怀孕三个月的有一天…- 你们的关系？
- On my mother's side, the Ardens. - No, your marriage bed.
我母亲那方的，亚登家族- 不，你们的婚姻关系
Four years and a hundred miles away in Stratford.
四年而且在一百五十公里外的斯特拉福
A cold bed, too, since the twins were born.
双胞胎出生后，她就很冷淡
Banishment was a blessing.
对我不理不睬反而是件好事
So, now you are free to love-- - Yet cannot love, nor write it.
那你就可以自由去爱啦- 但我无法爱，也无法写
Here is a-- a bangle...
这里有一个…手镯…
found in Psyche's temple on Olympus.
在奥林匹斯山的赛克宫找到的
Cheap at fourpence.
才四便士
Write your name on a paper and feed it into the snake.
把你的名字写在纸上塞进蛇的嘴里
Will it restore my gift?
我的天赋就能恢复？
The woman who wears the snake will dream of you, and your gift will return.
戴上它的女人会迷上你，你的天赋也能恢复
Words will flow like a river.
你会文思泉涌
See you next week.
下礼拜再见
Now where? - To the palace at Whitehall.
现在去那儿？－霭赫宫殿
All right.
好
Hello, Will.
嗨，威廉
Prithee, Mr. Kempe. Break a leg.
肯比先生、祝你好运
- You too, good Crab. - Crab's nervous. He's never played the palace.
克拉，你也好运　- 他紧张、从没在皇宫表演过
When will you write me a tragedy, Will?
威廉，写个悲剧给我吧？
- I could do it. - No, they would laugh at Seneca if you played it.
我会演的－不，你会被人笑死
There is no dog in the first scene, Mr. Kempe, thank you.
第一场戏没有狗，谢谢你，肯比先生
- How goes it, Will? - I'm still owed money for this play, Burbage.
威廉，最近好吗？- 你还欠我这出戏的钱
Not by me. I only stole it.
我不欠你，我是偷来的
My sleeve wants for a button, Mistress Rosaline.
我袖子掉了个扣子，洛丝琳小姐
Where were my seamstress' eyes?
裁缝师的眼睛长到哪儿去了？
When are you coming over to the Chamberlain's Men? - When I have 50 pounds.
你何时要加入张伯伦的剧组？- 等你付我50镑后
- You writing? - A comedy. All but done.
你剧本写了？一个喜剧。快写完了
A pirate comedy.
一个海盗的喜剧
- Wonderful. - Bring it tomorrow.
好极了－明天带来
- It's for Henslowe. He paid me. Ten pounds. - You're a liar.
给汉斯乐的。他付我10镑　你说谎
- He wants Romeo for Ned and the Admiral's Men.
他想把罗密欧给尼得和阿德曼的人演
- Mmm. Ned's wrong for it.
尼得的人不适合
Will?
威廉？
- Here's two sovereigns. I'll give you another two when I see the pages. - Done.
这里有两个金币。等我看到剧本再付给你两个
Burbage, I will see you hanged for a pickpocket.
你会因扒窃罪被吊死
The queen has commanded it. She loves a comedy.
是女王命令的　她喜欢看喜剧
And the Master of the Revels favors us.
而且是飨宴官挑我们演的
And what favor does Mr. Tilney receive from you?
提尔尼先生收了你什么好处？
- Ask him. - She comes!
去问他啊　她来了
Cease to persuade, my loving Proteus.
别说了，我亲爱的普特斯
Home-keeping youth have ever homely wits,
待在家里的年轻人总是平庸
were it not affection chains thy tender days...
若非爱连起一串温柔的日子…
When will you write me a sonnet, Will?
给我写一首十四行诗？
- I've lost my gift. - You left it in my bed.
我已失去了我的天赋　你掉在我床上了
Come to look for it again.
再来我这儿找啊
Are you to be my muse, Rosaline?
洛丝琳，你愿做我的灵感吗？
Burbage has my keeping,
波贝拥有我的身体
but you have my heart.
你却拥有我全部的心
You see? The consumptives plot against me.
那些观众又不捧场了
Will Shakespeare has a play.
威廉·莎士比亚写了部戏
Let's go and cough through it.
我们去看然后一路咳到底
My father weeping; my mother wailing;
我父亲在流泪　母亲在哭泣
our maid howling; our cat wringing her hands.
我家的女仆哀嚎；我家的猫扭着它的手
Yet did not this coldhearted cur...
可是这个铁石心肠的…
shed one tear--
…不流泪…
You see? Comedy.
你看？喜剧
Love, and a bit with a dog.
爱情，再凑上一条狗
That's what they want.
那是他们要的
He is a stone, a very pebble stone,
他心硬如石，铁石心肠
and has no more pity in him than a dog!
可怜他跟可怜狗差不多
A Jew would have wept to have seen our parting.
连犹太人都会为我们分离而流泪
Now the dog all this while sheds not a tear, nor speaks a word--
这条狗却不流一滴泪，也不说句话－－
Well played, Master Crab!
演得真好，克拉先生
I commend you!
我嘉奖你
What light is light...
如果见不着丝薇亚…
if Silvia be not seen?
…那种光才算光？
What joy is joy...
如果丝薇亚不在身旁
if Silvia be not by?
那种欢乐才叫欢乐？
Unless it be to think that she is by...
除非想着她在身旁
and feed upon the shadow of perfection.
从接近完美的她获得灵感
Except I be by Silvia in the night,
如果夜晚不能依偎丝薇亚
there is no music in the nightingale.
夜莺歌唱也不悦耳
Unless I look on Silvia in the day,
如果白天不能看着丝薇亚
there is no day for me to look upon.
我将不能面对白天
Did you like Proteus or Valentine best?
你喜欢普鲁提斯还是华伦泰
Proteus for speaking. Valentine for looks.
普鲁提斯会念台词，华伦泰英俊
Oh, I liked the dog for laughs.
哦，我喜欢狗引起的笑闹
Silvia, I did not care for much.
我不太喜欢丝薇亚
His fingers were red from fighting...
他的手指因为打架而成红色
and he spoke like a schoolboy at lessons.
而且他像个被训叱的学生
Stage love will never be true love...
舞台上的爱永远不是真爱
while the law of the land has our heroines being played by pipsqueak boys in petticoats.
小男生穿着女装演女主角
- Oh, when can we see another? - When the queen commands it.
什么时候再看一出戏- 当女皇要看的时候
No, but at the playhouse. Nurse!
不，去剧场看，奶娘
Be still. Playhouses are not for wellborn ladies.
剧场不是有身份淑女去的
Oh! I'm not so wellborn.
我不是那么高贵
Well-monied is the same as wellborn,
有钱就高贵
and well-married is more so.
嫁入侯门也一样
Lord Wessex was looking at you tonight.
今晚威克赛阁下一直看着你
All the men at court are without poetry.
在宫廷的所有男人都是市侩
If they see me, they see my father's fortune.
他们看我，是看我父亲的财富
I will have poetry in my life,
我要生命充满着诗
and adventure.
And love. Love above all.
以及爱，爱情至上
Like Valentine and Silvia?
像华伦泰与丝薇亚
No, not the artful postures of love,
不，不是虚假的爱
but love that overthrows life.
是刻骨铭心的爱
Unbiddable, ungovernable, like a riot in the heart,
不顾一切，不受控制，心潮澎湃
and nothing to be done, come ruin or rapture.
自由自在，随它毁灭或着心醉神迷
Love as there has never been in a play.
这种爱一定演不出来
I will have love, or I will end my days as--
我一定得有这种爱，否则我会终我余生做…
As a nurse?
做个奶娘
Oh, but I would be Valentine and Silvia too.
喔，我也会像华伦泰和丝薇亚
Oh, good nurse, God save you, and good night.
喔，我的女子奶娘，上帝保佑你，晚安
I would stay asleep my whole life...
如果能梦到自己成为演员
if I could dream myself into a company of players.
我愿睡一辈子
Clean your teeth while you dream, then.
谴做梦一逞清你的牙齿吧
Now spit.
现在吐出来
This time the boots are coming off.
这一次鞋子是脱掉的
- What have I done? - The theaters have all been closed down by the plague.
我做了什么？剧场因为瘟疫关门
- Oh, that. - By order of the Master of the Revels.
哦，是这件事　这是飨晏官的命令
Mr. Fennyman, allow me to explain about the theater business.
费尼门先生，请听我解释剧场的生意
The natural condition is one of insurmountable obstacles on the road to imminent disaster.
自然的灾害非人力所控制
- So what do we do? - Nothing.
我们现在怎么办- 什么也不做
- Strangely enough, it all turns out well. - How?
真奇怪，结果否极泰来　怎么会这样？
I don't know. It's a mystery.
我也不知道　这是个谜
Shall I kill him, Mr. Fennyman?
费尼门先生，我可把他宰了？
The theaters are reopened...
剧场又开门了
by order of the Master of the Revels!
这是飨宴官的命令
The theaters are reopened!
剧场又开门了
Mr. Fennyman.
Mr. Tilney has reopened the playhouses.
提尔尼先生的剧场又开张了
If you wouldn't mind.
对不起
Where's the play?
剧本呢
Oh, it's coming. It's coming.
噢，快来了，就快来了
It's coming.
就快来了
Will!
威廉
Will, I have wonderful news.
威廉，我有天大的好消息
So have l. Romeo and Rosaline, scene one.
罗密欧与罗莎琳，第一场
God, I'm good!
上帝呀，我真行
Rosaline? You mean Ethel.
罗莎琳？你是指爱索
Richard?
理查？
Burbage!
波贝！
Mr. Tilney.
提尔尼先生
Like you, I found him not at home.
跟你一样，我发现他不在家
I would've made you immortal.
我原本会捧得你大红大紫
Tell Burbage he has lost a new play by Will Shakespeare.
告诉波贝，莎士比亚剧本没他的份
What does Burbage care of that?
波贝在乎？
He's readying the Curtain for Kit Marlowe.
他在整理卡登剧场要演马罗的剧本
- You've opened the playhouses? - I have, Master Shakespeare.
你把剧场开张了？是的，莎士比亚先生
But the plague-- - Yes, I know.
但是瘟疫？这个我知道
But he was always hanging around the house.
但是他常常在剧场流连
The special today is a pig's foot marinated in juniper berry vinegar,
今晚的特餐是酸猪脚草莓
served on a buckwheat pancake-- - Will!
另加蔫麦薄饼…　威廉！
Have you finished?
写完了没？
Yes, nearly.
快了
- Good morning, Master Nol. You will have a nice part. - Yes!
早安，罗先生，你会有一个好的角色
- We'll need Ralph for the pirate king. - Clear that bloody table!
我们要劳尔夫做海盗王　把那个桌子清出来
None other than the Admiral's Men are out on tour.
原有阿得曼演员都不在
I need actors!
我要演员
Those of you who are unknown will have a chance to be known!
想出名的有机会了
- What about the money, Mr. Henslowe? - It won't cost you a penny!
汉斯乐先生，薪水如何？　你不需付一分钱
Auditions in half an hour!
半个钟头内面试
Ralph Bagswell, I'd have a part for you,
劳尔夫，我有一个角色给你
but, alas, I hear you are a drunkard's drunkard.
但是，我听说你是醉猫之王
Never when I'm working.
我工作时不喝酒
Never when I'm working!
Get me to drink mandragora.
来一杯曼陀罗华酒
Straight up, Will?
威廉，要纯的？
Give my friend a beaker of your best brandy.
给我的朋友一杯最好的白兰地
Kit.
企特
- How goes it, Will? - Wonderful. Wonderful.
近况如何，威廉？　不错，不错
- Burbage says you have a play. - I have, and the chinks to show for it.
波贝说你有一个剧本　当然有，看这些钱
I insist. A beaker for Mr. Marlowe.
我坚持　给马罗一大杯酒
I hear you have a new play for the Curtain.
我听说你为卡登写了个剧本
Not new. My Doctor Faustus.
不是新的。“医生佛陀士”
Ah. I love your early work.
我喜欢你早期的作品
"Was this the face that launched a thousand ships...
“是否就是这张脸}L发动了千艘战舰…
and burnt the topless towers of llium?"
“…把特洛伊城烧光？”
I have a new one nearly finished, and better.
我有一个剧本快完成了，比这个更好
The Massacre at Paris.
巴黎大屠杀
- Whew. Good title. - Mmm. Yours?
剧名真好　你的？
Romeo and Ethel, the Pirate's Daughter.
罗密欧与爱索，海盗的女儿
Yes, I know. I know.
是的，我知道
What is the story?
故事是什么？
Well, there's this pirate--
有一个海盗…
In truth, I have not written a word.
老实说，我还没写呢
Romeo.
罗密欧
Romeo is ltalian,
罗密欧是意大利人
always in and out of love.
常常恋爱又失恋
Yes, that's good. Until he meets--
是的，真好。直到他遇见…
- Ethel. - Do you think?
爱索
- The daughter of his enemy. - The daughter of his enemy.
他敌人的女儿　他敌人的女儿
His best friend is killed in a duel...
他的好朋友在决斗中被杀…
by Ethel's brother, or something-- His name is Mercutio.
被爱索的兄弟，或者什么…他的名字是马库修
Mercutio. Good name.
马库修　好名字
- Will! They're waiting for you! - Yes, I'm coming.
威廉！他们在等你　来啦
Good luck with yours, Kit.
企特，祝你幸运
- I thought your play was for Burbage. - This is a different one.
我以为你剧本是给波贝的　这个不一样
A different one you haven't written?
不一样的还没写？
Was this the face...
“是否就是这张脸孔…
that launched a thousand ships...
“…发动了千艘战舰…
and burnt the topless towers of llium?
“…把特洛伊城烧光？”
Thank you.
谢谢
Was this the face that launched a thousand ships...
“是否就是这张脸孔发动了千艘战舰…
and burnt the top-- topless towers of llium? - Thank you!
“…把特洛伊城烧光？”　谢谢！
Was this the face...
“是否就是这张脸孔…
that launched a thousand ships and burnt the topless--
“…发动了千艘战舰而且烧光高耸入云的…”
I would like to give you something from Faustus by Christopher Marlowe.
我要引用马罗在佛陀士剧中的一段
- How refreshing. - ...the topless towers of llium?
“…高耸入云的特洛伊城？
Sweet Helen, make me immortal with a kiss.
“亲爱的海伦，你的一吻令我倾倒
W-Was this the f--
“是不是这个…”
Very good, Mr. Wabash. Report to the property master.
太好了，瓦贝斯先生，请到道具主任处报道
My tailor wants to be an actor.
我的裁缝也想做演员
I have a few debts here and there.
我东欠债西欠债
Well, that seems to be everybody.
看起来面试完了
- Did you see a Romeo? - I did not.
你看到一个合格的罗密欧吗？　我没有？
Well, I to my work, you to yours.
好啦，我做完了，该你了
Oh, God.
May I begin, sir?
先生，我可以开始吗？
- Your name? - Thomas Kent.
贵姓？　汤玛士·肯特
I-l would like to do a speech by a writer who commands the heart of every player.
我要念一段名家作品它令每一个演员心神震荡
What light is light...
那种光才算光…
if Silvia be not seen?
…如果见不着丝薇亚：？
What joy is joy if Silvia be not by?
如果她不在身旁什么叫欢乐？
Unless it be to think that she is by...
除非想着她在身旁
and feed upon the shadow of perfection.
用她的完美形象滋润我
Except I be by Silvia in the night,
如果夜晚不能依偎丝薇亚
there is no music in the nightingale.
夜莺歌唱也不悦耳
Unless I look on Silvia in the day,
如果白天不能看着丝薇亚
there is no day for me to look upon.
我将不能面对白天
She is my essence, and I leave to be if I be not--
我无法少了她，如果我不－－
- Take off your hat! - My hat?
把你的帽子脱掉　我的帽子？
Where'd you learn how to do that?
你从哪学来念这些的？
I-- - Let me see you. Take off your hat.
我- 让我看看你，把你帽子脱掉
- Are you M-Master Shakespeare? - Wait there.
你是莎士比亚先生？　在那等着
Wait there!
在那等着
- Will, w-where are the pages? - Where is the boy?
威廉，剧本在哪？　男孩到那去了？
B-B-B-Break a leg!
祝你好运
Sir, will you buy my sweet orange?
先生，要买甜橘子吗？
Hey!
Everybody ready? All away!
大家都准备好了吗？全让开
- Follow that boat! - Right you are, governor.
跟着那条船　是的，先生
I know your face. Are you an actor?
我认得你的脸，你是演员？
- Yes. - Yes, I think I've seen you in something.
是的　对，我想我在戏里看过你
- That one about a king. - Really?
就是关于一个国王那出。　真的？
I had that Christopher Marlowe in my boat once.
克里斯多夫·马罗也坐过一次我的船
- Do you know that house? - Sir Robert De Lesseps.
你认得那栋房子吗？　罗伯·德·勒沙爵士的房子
Where is she? Our guests are upon us!
她去哪啦？客人随时会到
Lord Wessex, too, bargaining for a bride.
还有韦赛斯阁下，要找新娘
My husband will have it settled tonight.
我丈夫今晚会把婚事决定
Stamped, sealed and celebrated.
正式答应并且庆祝
Tomorrow he drags me off to the country,
明天他带我去乡下
and it will be three weeks gone before we return from our estates.
要三个礼拜才会由庄园回来
God save you, Mother.
母亲，上帝保佑你
Hot water, Nurse.
奶娘，给我点热水
I seek Master Thomas Kent.
我找汤玛士·肯特先生
- Who, sir? - The actor.
找哪位？　那位演员
- Who asks for him? - Will Shakespeare.
谁找他？　威廉·莎士比亚
Poet, playwright of the Rose.
诗人，玫瑰剧场的作家
Master Kent...
肯特先生…
is my nephew.
…是我的侄子
I will wait.
我等着
Much good may it do you.
那你等着吧
"Romeo Montague,
“罗密欧·蒙特古
a Young Man of Verona."
“威洛纳的年青人
Verona again?
又是威洛纳？
"A comedy of quarreling families...
“家族间口角的喜剧…
reconciled in the discovery of Romeo...
“…发现罗密欧是卡布雷家
to be the very same Capulet cousin...
“…表兄而宣告和解…
stolen from the cradle and fostered to manhood by his Montague mother...
“…在摇篮中被偷走由蒙特古家母亲抚养成人…
that was robbed of her own child by the pirate king."
“…而母亲自己的孩子却被海盗王抢走。”
Your mother and your father--
你父母亲…
From tomorrow, away in the country for three weeks!
从明天起，要到乡下去三个礼拜
Is Master Shakespeare not handsome?
莎士比亚先生不英俊吗
- He looks well enough for a charlatan. - Oh, Nurse!
走江湖骗人够英俊了　哦，奶娘！
He would give Thomas Kent...
他会给汤玛士·肯特
the life of Viola De Lesseps' dreaming.
薇奥拉梦想的生活
My lady, when your parents return, I will tell.
小姐，你父母亲回来，我要告诉他们
You will not tell.
你不会讲的
As I love you and you love me,
因为我爱你，你爱我
you will bind my breast and buy me a boy's wig.
你会把我胸束平，买顶男孩假发给我
Master Plum. What business here?
普勒先生，来这作什么？
The five schilling business, Will.
威廉，我来赚钱的
We play for the dancing.
我们替舞会演奏
Hyah! Hyah, hyah!
I seek Master Thomas Kent.
我找汤玛士·肯特先生
Musicians don't eat. Sir Robert's orders.
音乐家不准吃　爵士的命令
She's a beauty, my lord,
阁下，她是个美人
as would take a king to church for the dowry of a nutmeg.
即使是穷家女国王也会娶她
My plantations in Virginia are not mortgaged for a nutmeg.
我在维吉尼亚的大农场可不娶穷女子
I have an ancient name which will bring you preferment...
我家名声显赫会带给你名利
when your grandson is a Wessex.
如果你孙子姓韦赛斯
- Is she fertile? - Oh, she will breed.
她能生孩子吗　她能
- If she do not, send her back. - Is she obedient?
如果不会生，把她送回来　她听话吗？
As any mule in Christendom.
跟骡子一样听话
But if you are the man to ride her,
如果你跟她上床
there are rubies in the saddlebag.
她真是块宝
I like her.
我喜欢她
By all the stars in heaven.
众多美女中
Who is she?
她是谁？
Viola De Lesseps? Dream on, Will.
薇奥拉？威廉，别做梦了
Master Shakespeare.
莎士比亚先生
My lady Viola.
薇奥拉小姐
My lord.
阁下
I have spoken with your father.
我与令尊谈过了
So, my lord? I speak with him every day.
又怎样？我每天和他说话
Good sir.
先生
I heard you were a poet.
听说你是诗人
A poet of no words?
诗人辞穷啦？
Poet?
诗人？
I was a poet till now, but I've seen beauty that puts my poems...
我自认是诗人，而美女居然把我的诗…
at one with the talking ravens in the Tower.
和伦敦塔里聒噪的乌鸦相比
- How do I offend, my lord? - By coveting my property.
我怎么得罪你啦，阁下？　你垂涎我的女人
I cannot shed blood in her house, but I will cut your throat anon.
我不能在她家流血，但是改天我会切断你的喉咙
Do you have a name?
你叫什么名字？
Christopher Marlowe, at your service.
克里斯多夫·马罗，请指教
Romeo. Romeo.
罗密欧　罗密欧
A Young Man of Verona.
威洛纳的年青人
A comedy by William Shakespeare.
威廉莎士比亚的喜剧
- My lady! - Who is there?
小姐！　谁在下？
- Will Shakespeare. - Madam!
莎士比亚　小姐！
Anon, good nurse, anon.
来啦，奶娘，来啦
- Oh, Master Shakespeare. - The same, alas.
哦，莎士比亚先生　唉，还是老样
But why "alas"?
为什么要“唉”？
- A lowly player. - Alas, indeed.
一个低下的演员
For I thought you the highest poet of my esteem...
我可把你当成我最欣赏的卓越诗人
and a writer of plays that capture my heart.
能掳获我心的剧作家
- Oh, I am him too. - Madam!
哦，那也是我。　小姐！
Anon! I will come again.
来啦！我会再回来
Oh, I am fortune's fool. I will be punished for this.
哦，命运戏弄我，我这样作会被惩罚的
Oh, my lady, my love!
哦，小姐，我的爱
If they find you here, they will kill you.
如果被发现，他们会杀了你
- You can bring them with a word. - Oh, not for the world.
你一出声他们就会来　噢，我决不会这么作
- Madam! - Anon!
小姐！　来啦！
Draw, if you be men!
“如果是男子汉，拔剑吧！
Gregory, remember thy swashing blow!
“葛雷格瑞，给他重重一击！
Part, fools! Put up your swords. You know not what you do.
“住手，傻瓜！把剑收起来、你们不知道在作什么？”
It starts well, then it's all long-faced about some Rosaline.
开头很好，接着就全是悲愁的关于什么洛斯琳
Where's the comedy, Will? Where's the dog?
喜剧在哪儿？狗在哪儿？
Do you think it's funny?
你认为好笑吗？
I was a pirate king, now I'm a nurse. That's funny.
我先当海盗王，现在变奶娘。这很好笑
We are six men short, and those we have will be overparted ranters...
还差六人，眼前这些多余角色都是喧喧嚷嚷…
and stutterers who should be sent back to the stews.
和结结巴巴的人，全该送回贫民窟
My Romeo's let me down. I see disaster.
罗密欧让我失望，灾难大了
We are four acts short, if you're looking for disaster.
我们还缺四幕，这才是大灾难呢
- Sir! - Who are you, master?
先生！　先生！你是谁？
I'm Ethel, sir, the pirate's daughter.
先生，我演爱索，海盗女儿
I'll be damned if you are!
如果是你演我真该死了
Your attention, please!
请注意
- Gentlemen, thank you! - You are welcome.
各位先生，谢谢　- 不客气
- Who's that? - Nobody. He's the author.
那是谁？ -谁也不是，他是作者
We are about to embark on a great voyage.
我们即将展开伟大之旅
It is customary to make a little speech on the first day.
习惯上首演那天都会先有一小段演讲
It does no harm. Authors like it.
没有坏处，作者都喜欢
You want to know what parts you are to receive. All will be settled as we--
你们想知道自己接演什么角色、一切会安排
I'll do it.
让我来说
Now listen to me, you dregs.
你们这群垃圾，听我说
Actors are ten a penny,
演员好找得很
and l, Hugh Fennyman, hold your nuts in my hand.
你们全握在我休·费尼门的手上
Huzzah!
好啊！
The Admiral's Men are returned to the house!
阿得曼剧组的人回剧场喽
Huzzah!
好啊！
尼德
Henslowe!
汉斯乐
Earl! Good to see you.
厄尔！真高兴见到你
Who is this?
这位是谁？
Silence, you dog!
你这小人，安静
I am Hieronimo.
我是赫若尼姆
I am Tamburlaine.
我是谭伯伦
I am Faustus.
我是佛斯特
I am Barabbas, the Jew of Malta.
我是马他犹太人里的巴拉巴
Oh, yes, Master Will. I am Henry the Sixth.
威廉先生，我是亨利六世
What is the play, and what is my part?
是那出剧？我演什么角色？
Uh, one moment, sir-- - Who are you?
先生，等一下…　- 你是谁？
I'm, um-- I'm the money.
出钱的人
Then you may remain,
留下来吧
so long as you remain silent.
只要你不出声
Pay attention. You will see how genius creates a legend.
注意！请看天才如何创造传奇
- Thank you, sir. - We are in desperate want of a Mercutio, Ned.
先生，谢谢你- 我们急需人饰演马库修
A young nobleman of Verona.
威洛纳的年轻贵族
- And the title of this piece? - Mercutio.
这出剧什么名？- 马库修
Is it?
是吗？
I will play him.
那我来演他
Mr. Pope. Mr. Philips. Welcome.
伯普先生，菲利先生，欢迎
George Bryan. James Armitage.
乔治·拜恩，詹姆·阿特
Sam, my pretty one!
山姆，我的美人儿
- Are you ready to fall in love again? - I am, Master Shakespeare.
你准备好再堕情网了吗？ - 准备好了
Your voice. Have they dropped?
你的声音，你变声了吗？
No! No. A touch of cold only.
没有！只是着凉了
Master Henslowe, you have your actors... except Thomas Kent.
除了汤玛士·肯特，演员都到齐了
I, uh, I saw his Tamburlaine, you know.
我看过他演谭伯伦，你知道
- It was wonderful. - Yes, I saw it.
演得真好- 是的
Of course, such mighty writing.
当然，这么有力的作品
There's no one like Marlowe.
没人比得上马罗
Better fortune, boy.
祝你下次好运，孩子
I was in a play.
我演过戏
They cut my head off in Titus Andronicus.
在台特·安卓尼戏里我被砍头
When I write plays, they'll be like Titus.
如果我写剧本要像台特一样
You admire it.
你欣赏它
I liked it when they cut heads off,
我喜欢砍头的情节
and the daughter mutilated with knives.
还有女孩用刀子自残
- What's your name? - John Webster.
你叫什么名字？　约翰·韦斯特
Here, kitty, kitty.
在这里，猫眯
Plenty of blood.
好多血
That's the only writing.
这是唯一好戏
I have to get back.
我得回去了
See, where he comes. So please you step aside.
看，他来了，请你先站旁边
I'll know his grievance, or be much denied.
我问他委屈，问不出别认我
I would thou wert so happy by thy stay to hear true shrift. Come, madam.
留下来，听他的真实告解
- Cut around him for now. - What? Who?
绕到旁边去　什么？
- Romeo. - The one who came with your letter.
罗密欧 给你捎信的那一位
- What? - Good morrow, cousin.
什么？　早安，堂哥
Is the day so young?
仍然是早上吗？
- But new struck nine. - Ay me. Sad hours seem long.
现在才九点。　唉，时间过的真慢
What sadness lengthens Romeo's hours?
有什么事让罗密欧如此的忧愁？
Not having that which having makes them short.
没有什么可让时光变短
- Good. - In love?
好 -恋爱了？
- Out. - Of love?
失恋了？-失恋了？
- Out of her favor where I am in love. - Don't spend it all at once.
我爱她但是她不爱我　不要太过发挥
Yes, sir.
是的，先生
- Do you understand me? - No, sir.
你了解我的意思？　不了解，先生
You're speaking about a baggage we never even meet.
这只是一位无足轻重的女人
What will be left in his purse when he meets his Juliet?
后来遇到他的茱莉叶该怎么办？
- Juliet? You mean Ethel. - God's teeth!
茱莉叶？你是指爱索
Am I to suffer this constant stream of interruption?
别打扰我
What will he do in Act Two, when he meets the love of his life?
他在第二幕遇到他此生至爱时，该怎么表现？
I-l'm very sorry, sir. I have not seen Act Two.
十分抱歉，我没看到第二幕
Of course you have not. I have not written it.
你当然没有、我还没写出来
Go once more.
再练一次
Will.
Where is Mercutio?
马库修呢？
Locked safe in here. I'll leave the scene in your safekeeping, Ned.
在这儿，我把这一幕保留给你
I have a sonnet to write.
我有十四行诗要写
Sonnet? You mean a play!
十四行诗？你是指剧本
For Lady Viola De Lesseps,
“薇奥拉．德·勒沙小姐亲启
by the hand of Thomas Kent.
“汤玛士·肯特转交”
"Shall I compare thee to a summer's day?
“我是否应把你比做夏日？
Thou art more lovely and more temperate.
“你是更美丽、更温柔
Rough winds do shake the darling buds of May--"
“狂风摇动着迷人的五月花蕾…”
Two hours at prayer!
祷告二个钟头
Lady Viola is pious, my lord.
薇奥拉小姐是虔诚的，阁下
Piety is for Sunday!
虔诚是礼拜日的事
And two hours of prayer is not piety, it is self-importance.
那不是虔诚，是自视过高
It would be better that you return tomorrow, my lord.
你最女子明天再来，阁下
It would be better if you'd tell her to get off her knees and show some civility...
你最好告诉她多献殷熟
to her six-day lord and master!
对另外六天的主人
Mmmph!
My lady Viola.
我的薇奥拉小姐
Lord Wessex. You've been waiting.
韦赛斯阁下，久候了
I am aware of it.
我知道
But it is beauty's privilege.
但那是美女的特权
You flatter, my lord.
恭维了，阁下
No. I have spoken to the queen.
我和女王谈过了
Her Majesty's consent is requisite when a Wessex takes a wife,
我娶妻时必须先得到女王的同意
and once given, her consent is her command.
她同意的即是命令
Do you intend to marry, my lord?
阁下，你打算结婚啦？
Your father should keep you better informed.
你父亲应该告诉你了
He has bought me for you.
他把你许配给了我
He returns from his estates to see us married two weeks from Saturday.
他二个礼拜后回来参加我们的婚礼
You are allowed to show your pleasure.
你现在可以表示你的快乐
But I do not love you, my lord.
但是我并不爱你，阁下
How your mind hops about.
你在胡思乱想些什么
Your father was a shopkeeper.
你的父亲是店主
Your children will bear arms, and I will recover my fortune.
而你将有地位，我将有财富
That is the only matter under discussion today.
今天谈论的只有这一件事
You will like Virginia.
你会喜欢维吉尼亚的
- Virginia? - Oh, yes.
维吉尼亚？　是啊
My fortune lies in my plantations. The tobacco weed.
我的财富全靠我农场里的烟草
I need 4,000 pounds to fit out a ship and put my investments to work.
我需要四千英镑买货赚钱
I fancy tobacco has a future.
我相信烟草是有前途的
We will not stay there long. Three or four years.
我们不会在那待太久，三、四年吧
But why me?
为什么选我？
It was your eyes.
是你的眼睛
No, your lips.
不，是你的唇
Will you defy your father and your queen?
你要违抗你的父亲和女王？
The queen has consented?
女王同意了？
She wants to inspect you.
她要见见你
At Greenwich, come Sunday.
礼拜日在格林威治
Be submissive, modest, grateful...
要恭顺、端庄、宜人
and brief.
和简洁
I will do my duty, my lord.
我会尽我的职责，阁下
"Master Will, poet dearest to my heart,
“威廉先生，我心中的诗人
I beseech you banish me from yours.
“我求你，把我从你心里忘了
I am to marry Lord Wessex.
“我将要嫁给韦赛斯阁下
A daughter's duty...
“一个做女儿的责任
and the queen's command."
“…以及女王的命令。”
Gentlemen upstage Ladies downstage
“男士们台上，女士们台下
Are you a lady Mr. Kent
“肯特先生你是女士吗？”
I'm very sorry, sir.
十分抱歉，先生
We're gonna have to do it again.
我们得再练一次
You did not like the speech?
你不喜欢这台词？
No, the speech is excellent.
没有，台词非常的好
"Oh, then I see Queen Mab hath been with you."
“我看见你和小仙女在一起。”
Excellent, and a good length.
太棒了，长短刚好
But then he disappears for the length of a bible.
但是他这么久没有出现
There. You have this duel.
啊、你有场决斗的戏
A skirmish of words and swords such as I never wrote, nor anyone.
唇枪舌剑，我从未写过，任何人也没写过。
He dies with such passion and poetry as you ever heard.
他死的激情而诗意
"A plague on both your houses!"
“咒你们两家都闹瘟疫！”
He dies?
他死了？
- Ohh! - Will!
Where are my pages?
我的剧本在那儿？
Did you give her my letter?
你把我的信给她了吗？
And this is for you!
这是给你的
Oh, Thomas, she has cut my strings.
喔，汤玛士，她不理我了
I'm unmanned,
我完了
unmended and unmade,
完了，毁了
Iike a puppet in a box.
就像在盒子里的木偶
- Writer, is he? - Row your boat!
他是作家吗？　摇你的船！
She tells me to keep away.
她叫我离她远点
She is to marry Lord Wessex! What should I do?
她要嫁人了！我该怎么办？
If you love her, you must do as she asks.
你爱她，就照她所说的做
- And break her heart and mine? - It is only yours you can know.
伤她和我的心？　只是你自己的心吧
She loves me, Thomas!
她爱我，汤玛士
- Does she say so? - No.
她有这么说？　没有
And yet she does where the ink has run with tears.
她爱我，纸上留下了她的泪痕
Was she weeping when she gave you this? - Uh--
她给你信的时候在哭吗？
- Her letter came to me by the nurse. - Your aunt.
她的奶娘给我的　你的姑妈
Yes, my aunt.
是的，我的姑妈
But perhaps she wept a little.
也许她掉了些泪
Tell me how you love her, Will.
你爱她多少，威廉
Like a sickness and its cure together.
爱的欲仙欲死
Oh, yes.
是啊
Like rain and sun.
如雨露阳光
Like cold and heat.
似水火交融
Is your lady beautiful?
你家小姐美吗？
Since I came here from the country,
因为我从乡下来
I have not seen her close.
没有仔细的看过她
Tell me, is-- is she beautiful?
告诉我…她美吗？
Thomas, if I could write with the beauty of her eyes,
但愿我能描绘她美丽的双眼
I was born to look in them and know myself.
我是为她那双秀目而生
A-A-And her lips?
她的唇呢？
Her lips?
她的唇？
The early morning rose would whither on the branch if it could feel envy.
如果清晨的玫瑰会忌妒的话它也会枯萎在枝头
And her voice, like lark's song?
那么她的声音，似百灵鸟？
Deeper, softer. None of your twittering larks.
更亮，更柔，不像吱吱喳喳的百灵鸟
I would banish nightingales from her garden before they interrupt her song.
在夜莺打扰她唱歌之前我会将它们逐出花园
- Ah, she sings too? - Constantly.
她会唱歌？　总是在唱
Without doubt. And plays the lute. She has a natural ear.
毫无疑问的，她会弹诗琴。她有音乐的天赋
And her bosom.
还有她的酥胸
Did I mention her bosom?
我有提过她的酥胸？
What of her bosom?
她的酥胸如何？
Oh, Thomas, a pair of pippins...
那是双苹果
as round and rare as golden apples.
又圆又嫩像个金苹果
I think milady is wise to keep your love at a distance.
我家小姐和你保持距离是明智之举
For what lady could live up to it close to...
哪家小姐能满足你的期许
when her eyes and lips and voice may be no more beautiful than mine.
何况她并不比我美
Besides, can a--can a lady of wealth and noble marriage...
一位和贵族联婚的富家女
Iove happily with a bankside poet and player?
能快乐地和河逞诗人相爱吗？
Yes, by God!
可以，绝对可以
Love knows nothing of rank or riverbank.
爱是不分等级的
It will spark between a queen and the poor vagabond who plays the king.
饰演国王的流浪汉和女王也会谱出恋曲
Their love should be minded by each,
他们的爱是互动的
for love denied blights the soul we owe to God.
否定爱情是对神的一种侮蔑
So tell my lady William Shakespeare waits for her in the garden.
告诉你家小姐，在花园里等她
But what of Lord Wessex?
那韦赛斯阁下怎么办？
For one kiss I would defy a thousand Wessexes.
为了一个吻，我会奋不顾身
Oh, Will.
噢，威廉
Thank you, my lady.
谢谢你，小姐
Lady?
小姐？
Viola De Lesseps. Known her since she was this high.
薇奥拉·德·勒沙，我认识她
Wouldn't deceive a child.
她骗不了人
Strangely enough, I'm a bit of a writer meself.
凑巧，我也算是个作
It wouldn't take you long to read it.
不很长的
I expect you'd know all the booksellers!
我想你认识所有的书商
Can you love a fool?
你会爱上一个傻瓜吗？
Can you love a player?
你会爱上一个演员吗？
Wait!
等等
You're still a maid, and perhaps as mistook in me as I was mistook in Thomas Kent.
你还是处女，别被我骗了像是汤玛士·肯特蒙骗我
Are you the author of the plays of William Shakespeare?
你是不是威廉．莎士比亚？
I am.
我是
Then kiss me again, for I am not mistook.
我没弄错，再吻我一次
I do not know how to undress a man.
我不知道如何为男士宽衣
It is strange to me too.
我也不懂
Go to. Go to.
走开
I would not have thought it.
我从来没有想到
There is something better than a play.
有比戏剧更好的东西
There is.
是有的
Even your play.
比你的剧本还好
Oh?
And that was only my first try.
这是我的第一次
Will.
You would not leave me.
你不要走
I must.
我必须走
Look how pale the window.
看这窗已泛白
Moonlight.
那是月光
Mmm, no. The morning rooster woke me.
不，是鸡呜唤醒了我
It was the owl. Come to bed.
是猫头鹰，睡吧
Oh, let Henslowe wait.
哦，让汉斯乐等吧
Mr. Henslowe?
汉斯乐先生吗？
Mmm, let him be damned for his pages.
管他要什么剧本
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
哦，不，不
There is time. Mmm! It is still dark.
还早呢！天还黑
- It's broad day. The rooster tells us so. - It was the owl.
天亮了，晨鸡报晓了。　是猫头鹰
Believe me, love, it was the owl--
相信我，是猫头鹰
You would leave us players without a scene to read today?
你要耽误排演吗？
My lady?
小姐
The house is stirring. It is a new day.
屋里人都醒了，是新的一天
It is a new world.
是个新世界
Good pilgrim, you do wrong your hand too much,
朝圣者，你的手并不那么粗
which mannerly devotion shows in this.
你手的触碰已显示你的虔敬
For saints have hands that pilgrims' hands do touch,
圣者也用手触碰来招呼朝圣者
and palm to palm is holy palmers' kiss.
而朝圣者用双手相握来致敬
Have not saints lips, and holy palmers too?
圣者与朝圣者难道没有唇？
Aye, pilgrim.
有啊，朝圣者
Lips that they must use in prayer.
他们的唇是用来祈祷的
Oh, then, dear saint, let lips do what hands do.
那么，让唇像手一样相触吧
They pray.
用唇来祷告
Grant thou, lest faith turn to despair.
信心才不会成绝望
Saints do not move, though grant for prayers' sake.
圣者不会行动，虽然已应许你的祷告
It's you.
该你了
Suffering cats!
别这样
Then move not...
那就不要动
while my prayer's effect I take.
让我承受我所祈祷的吧
Thus from my lips, by thine my sin is purged.
我的唇伴着你的唇，洗净罪恶
Then have my lips the sin that they have took.
现在我的唇也染上你的罪
Sin from my lips? Oh, trespass sweetly urged. Give me my sin again.
多美的暗示、再把我的罪给我吧
Yes, yes! Um, not quite right.
对！不太对
It is more-- Let me.
应该更…让我来
Then have my lips the sin that they have took.
现在我的唇也染上你的罪
Sin from my lips? Oh, trespass sweetly urged. Give me my sin again.
多美的暗示、再把我的罪给我吧
- You kiss by the book. - Well, Will!
你的吻是研究过的 　啊，威廉！
It was lucky you were here.
真幸运你在这里
Why do not I write the rest of your play-- - Yes, yes!
我来写剩下的部分…　　是啊！
Uh, continue. Now the nurse. Where is Ralph?
继续，奶娘上场，鲁道夫在哪？
Madam, your mother craves a word with you.
小姐，你母亲要和你说话
- What is her mother? - Marry, bachelor,
她的母亲是谁？　玛莉，单身汉
her mother is the lady of the house, and a good lady...
她母亲是这屋子的女主人
and a wise and virtuous.
有智慧又有美德
I nursed her daughter that you talked withal.
她的女儿是我喂大的
I tell you, he that can lay hold of her...
谁若高攀她
shall have the chinks.
将有万贯家财
- Is she a Capulet? - Mmm.
她是卡布雷家族的人吗？
Oh, dear account! My life is my foe's debt.
代价真大！我的命在敌人手
Away. Be gone. The sport is at the best.
走吧，晚宴已经结束了
Aye, so I fear. The more is my unrest.
我想也是，我有点担心
Come hither, nurse. What is yon gentleman?
奶娘，那位绅士是谁？
The son and heir of old Tiberio.
是老提伯欧的儿子和继承人
Let it be night.
在夜晚
- What's he that follows here that would not dance? - I know not.
不跳舞的那人是谁？　我不知道
Go ask his name.
去问他的名字
If he be married, my grave is like to be my wedding bed.
但愿他还未结婚
No, do not go.
不要走
I must. I must.
我一定得走
- The only son of your great enemy. - Terrible.
他是你世仇的独生子　　糟糕
Simply... terrible!
真是…糟糕
"But soft, what light through yonder window breaks?
“是什么光线透过彼逞窗户？
It is the east,
“是从东方
and Juliet is the sun.
“而茱莉叶是太阳
Arise, fair sun, and kill the envious moon...
“鲜明的太阳，击溃妒嫉的月光
who is already sick and pale with grief...
“…月光已病弱苍白且哀伤
that thou, her maid, art far more fair than she."
“因你远比她更精美无瑕、
- Oh, Will. - Yes, some of it's speakable.
哦，威廉- 有些可用言语描述
"lt is my lady. Oh, it is my love!
“她是我的情，我的爱
Oh, that she knew she were!
“哦，她知道
The brightness of her cheek would shame those stars...
“她面颊灿烂的使群星羞愧
as daylight doth a lamp."
“…就如日光使灯无光。”
Her eyes in heaven would through the airy region...
她的双眸照过空气云层
stream so bright...
如此光亮
that birds would sing and think it were not night.
鸟儿无日无夜的歌唱
See how she leans her cheek upon her hand.
看她如此的用手托着脸颊
Oh, that I were a glove upon that hand,
哦，但愿我是那只手套
that I might touch that cheek.
就可贴着她的面颊
- Ay, me. - "Oh, Romeo.
哦，我的心
Romeo.
“哦，罗密欧，罗密欧
Wherefore art thou, Romeo?
“你在那里，罗密欧？
Deny thy father and--" - Deny thy father and refuse thy name.
“背离你的父且放弃你的名
Or, if thou wilt not, be but sworn my love,
如果不，只要你宣誓爱我
and I'll no longer be a Capulet.
我将不再姓卡布雷
Shall I hear more, or shall I speak at this?
我该继续听，还是对她说呢？
"What man art thou that thus bescreened in night...
“是谁躲在黑暗中…
so stumblest on my counsel?"
“…如此的窃听我的密秘？
By a name I know not how to tell thee who I am.
说到名字，我不知如何告诉你
My name, dear saint, is hateful to myself, because it is an enemy to thee.
我的名字是你仇家的名字
Had I it written I would tear the word.
如我已写下我将把它撕毁
"The orchard walls are high and hard to climb...
“这花园的围墙很高很难爬过去…
and the place death, considering who thou art,
“…而且以你是谁将成你死之地…
if any of my kinsmen find thee here.
“…如果我家人看到你在此
If they do see thee, they will murder thee."
“如果他们看到你，他们将会杀了你。”
Alack, there lies more peril in thine eye than 20 of their swords.
你的眼睛比二十把剑还厉害
Look thou but sweet, and I am proof against their enmity.
看到你如此甜美，仇恨伤不到我
Would not for the world they saw thee here.
以任何代价我不让他们看到你
I have night's cloak to hide me from their eyes.
我有夜行斗篷遮蔽，不会被发现
- And but thou love me let them find me here. - "Good night.
只要你爱我就让他们找到我
Good night,
“晚安
as sweet repose and rest come to thy heart...
“甜蜜地安眠到你心中
as that within my breast.
“…就像在我心中一样
Oh, wilt thou leave me so unsatisfied?"
“哦，你让我如此不满足吗？”
That's my line.
那是我的台词
Oh. It is mine too.
也是我的
Oh, wilt thou leave me so unsatisfied?
哦，你让我如此不满足吗？
What satifaction canst thou have tonight?
今晚你要的满足是什么？
The exchange of thy love's faithful vow for mine.
你爱的誓言与我的交换
"My bounty is as boundless as the sea.
我的情像大海无边
My love is deep.
我的爱也像大海一样深
The more I give to thee,
我给你越多
the more I have,
我拥有越多
for both are infinite."
两者都是无限的
Madam?
- I hear some noise within. Dear love, adieu. - Juliet!
我听到有声音，亲爱的，再见
- "Anon, good nurse." - Anon, good nurse. Sweet Montague, be true.
来了，好奶妈。　来了，好奶妈
"Stay but a little. I will come again."
稍候一下、我会再来
Stay but a little. I will come again.
稍候一下，我会再来
Oh, blessed, blessed night.
哦，这受祝福的，祝福的夜晚
"l am afeared...
我怕…
being in night, all this is but a dream.
…既是夜晚，一切只是梦
Too flattering sweet...
太让人喜爱的甜蜜…
to be substantial."
…不可能成真
To cease thy strife and leave me to my grief.
停止你的挣扎让我回到我的悲伤
A thousand times, good night.
祝你一千次的晚安
A thousand times the worse to want thy light.
千倍糟糕的是如果没有你的光
I cannot move in this dress. It makes me look like a pig.
穿着这身衣服我看来相只猪
I have no neck in this pig dress.
在猪衣里，我都没有颈子
- How is it? - It's all right.
怎么样？
Ned, I know, I know.
尼德，我知道，我知道
- It's good. - Oh?
它很好
The title won't do.
就是剧名不好
Ah.
Romeo and Juliet. Just a suggestion.
罗密欧与茱莉叶，只是建议
Thank you, Ned.
谢谢你，尼德
- You are a gentleman. - And you are a Warwickshire shit-house.
你真是位绅士- 你是华家狗屁房
- What o'clock tomorrow shall I send to thee? - By the hour of nine.
明天几点我来看你？　九点
I shall not fail. 'Tis 20 year till then.
我一定来　像要等二十年
I have forgot why I called thee back.
我忘了为什么叫你回来
- You mean no dog of any kind? - Shh! Silence.
你是说剧里没有狗？　　住嘴
The friar marries them in secret,
神父令他们密秘结婚
then Ned gets into a fight with one of the Capulets.
尼德和卡布雷家的一员打起来
Romeo tries to stop them and gets in Ned's way. I mean, in Mercutio's way.
罗密欧想阻止他们而挡住马库修
So Tybalt kills Mercutio, then Romeo kills Tybalt.
太伯特杀了马库修，罗密欧杀了太伯特
Then the prince banishes him from Verona.
王子将他逐出威洛纳
That must be when he goes on the voyage and gets shipwrecked...
该是他遇到船难了
on the island of the pirate king.
在海盗岛上
For God's sake, cease your prattling and get out!
别胡说八道滚开
Get out!
滚开
A thousand apologies.
千次道歉
Please.
请
And with a silken thread plucks it back again,
用丝线把他拉回来
so loving-jealous of his liberty.
爱的妒嫉不愿给他自由
- I would I were thy bird. - Sweet, so would l; yet I should kill thee with much cherishing.
但愿我是她的鸟儿 - 我害怕过份的爱会令你窒息
Good night. Good night.
晚安　晚安
Parting is such sweet sorrow, that I shall say good night till it be morrow.
离别甜美而凄凉，我愿整夜守候你
Sunday.
星期天
It is Sunday.
是星期天
I found something in my sleep.
在我睡觉时我有个灵感
The friar who married them will take up their destinies.
给他们主婚的神父将会支配他们的命运、
- But it will end well for love. - In heaven, perhaps.
但会因爱而完美 - 也许，在天堂吧
It is not a comedy I'm writing now.
我现在写的不是喜剧
A broad river divides my lovers.
大河阻隔了我的爱人
Family, duty, fate.
家庭，责任，命运
As unchangeable as nature.
与自然一样无法改变
Yes.
This is not life, Will.
这不是生活
It is a stolen season.
窃来的时光
- Be patient, my lord. - Patient?
耐性点，阁下 - 耐性？
Do you ask Her Majesty to be patient? - My Lord, I will go--
你要陛下有耐性？- 阁下，我去…
Sunday. Greenwich!
星期天　格林威治
Now, pay attention, nursie.
听着，奶娘
The queen-- Gloriana Regina,
女皇…伟大的女皇
God's chosen vessel, the radiant one who shines her light on us--
天定的人选，光芒四耀的人！
is at Greenwich today and prepared during the evening's festivities...
正在格林威治准备今晚的盛宴！
to bestow her gracious favor on my choice of wife.
为我选定的妻子
And if we're late for lunch, the old boot will not forgive!
如果迟到，那老女人可饶不了我们
So get you to my lady's chamber and produce her with or without her undergarments!
不论怎样，马上到居室带她出来
You cannot! Not for the queen herself!
不行！即使是女皇旨意
What will you have me do? Marry you instead?
那我该怎么做？嫁给你
To be the wife of a poor player.
做个穷演员的妻子
Can I wish that for Lady Viola except in my dreams?
我只能在梦中期待着薇奥拉吗？
And yet I would if I were free to follow my desire in the harsh light of day.
我希望白天亦能随心所欲
You follow your desire freely enough in the night.
在夜晚你已够随性了
- So, if that is all, to Greenwich I go. - Then I'll go with you.
多说无益，我要去格林威治　　我跟你去
- You cannot. Wessex will kill you. - I know how to fight.
不行，韦赛斯会杀了你，我知道如何打斗
Stage fighting.
舞台式打斗
Oh, Will.
噢，威廉
As Thomas Kent, my heart belongs to you,
身为肯特，我心属于你
but as Viola, the river divides us,
但身为薇奥拉，大河阻隔我俩
and I must marry Wessex a week from Saturday.
下星期六我必须嫁给韦赛斯
I'll drag her down by the queen's command!
出于女皇旨意，我要拖她下来
Good morning, my Lord.
早安
My lady. The tide waits for no man, but I swear it would wait for you.
光阴不侯人，但它必为你停留
Oh, here we come at last, my lord!
我们来晚了，阁下
Are you bringing your laundrywoman?
你要带着洗衣妇吗？
Her chaperone, my lady's country cousin.
她的伴护，小姐乡间的表亲
My, but you be a handsome gallant,
多俊美的年轻人
just as she said.
正如她所言
You may call me Miss Wilhelmina.
你可唤我薇米娜小姐
On a more fortuitous occasion, perhaps.
或许在更合适的场合
Oh, my Lord, you will not shake me off.
噢，阁下，你摆脱不了我的
Aye, she never needed me more. I swear by your britches.
她需要我陪伴
- Now? - Now.
现在？- 现在
The queen asks for you. Answer well.
女皇召见你，好好表现
- Is there a man? - A man, my lord?
有没有男人？ - 男人？
There was a man, a poet. A theater poet, I think.
有个男人，是个剧场诗人
- Does he come to the house? - A theater poet?
他去过宅邸？ - 剧场诗人？
An insolent penny-a-page rogue! Marlowe, he said. Christopher Marlowe.
傲慢的无名小卒！自称马罗，克里斯多夫·马罗
- Has he been to the house? - Marlowe?
他去过宅邸吗？- 马罗？
Oh, yes. He is the one.
噢，对。就是他
Lovely waistcoat. Shame about the poetry.
漂亮的背心　艺文界之耻
That dog!
那个混蛋！
Your Majesty.
陛下！
Stand up straight, girl.
起身，女孩
I've seen you.
我见过你
You are the one who comes to all the plays at Whitehall, at Richmond.
出席所有理查蒙，怀特宫上演剧码的就是你
Your Majesty.
陛下
What do you love so much?
你最爱什么？
Your Majesty-- - Speak up, girl!
陛下… - 说出来，女孩
I know who I am.
我知道我是谁
Do you love stories of kings and queens?
你喜欢宫廷式的爱情故事？
Of feats of arms?
冒险打斗故事？
Or is it courtly love?
还是梦幻爱情？
I love theater.
我爱剧院
To have stories acted for me by a company of fellows is indeed--
让一群演员将故事展现在我面前是...
They're not acted for you; they are acted for me. And?
他们并非为你表演，而是为我，说下去？
And I love poetry above all.
我最爱诗歌
Above Lord Wessex?
甚过韦赛斯阁下？
My lord, when you cannot find your wife,
阁下，当找不到你的妻子...
you better look for her at the playhouse.
...最好试试戏院
Playwrights teach us nothing about love.
在戏剧中学不到爱情
They make it pretty; they make it comical; or they make it lust.
他们让爱情美；让它喜乐；或充满欲念
They cannot make it true.
却无法成真
Oh, but they can.
他们做得到
I mean, Your Majesty, they-- they do not, they have... not,
我是指尚未做到
but I believe there is one who can.
但我相信有人做得到
My Lady Viola is young in the world.
薇奥拉小姐还太年轻
Your Majesty is wise in it.
陛下见解精辟
Nature and truth are the very enemies of playacting. I'll wager my fortune.
戏剧无法表现自然与真实，我愿用我的财产做赌注
I thought you were here because you had none.
我想你根本身无分文
- Well, no one will take your wager, it seems. - Fifty pounds.
似乎没有人要下注 - 50英镑
Fifty pounds?
50英镑？
A very worthy sum on a very worthy question.
价码不小，物有所值
Can a play show us the very truth and nature of love?
戏剧能展现爱的自然与真实吗？
I bear witness to the wager...
我愿替此赌注做见证...
and will be the judge of it as occasion arises.
...机会来临时，我会为此定夺
I have seen nothing to settle it yet.
但我还未碰见证据
Are there no more fireworks?
烟火结束了吗？
They would be soothing after the excitements of Lady Viola's audience.
在薇奥拉小姐精彩表演后，烟火可让我们平静些
Have her, then, but you are a lordly fool.
娶她吧，但是你是个贵族傻瓜
She's been plucked since I saw her last, and not by you.
她已被开苞了，但对像不是你
It takes a woman to know it.
女人的直觉
Marlowe.
马罗
Burbage?
波贝？
Huh? Who's there?
谁？
Marlowe.
马罗
You are playing my Dr. Faustus this afternoon.
下午“法斯图博士”可以上演
Don't spend yourself in sport.
别浪费精力
- What do you want, Kit? - My Massacre at Paris is complete.
干嘛，企特？ - “巴黎大屠杀”已完成
- What? You have the last act? - If you have the money.
什么？有最后一幕了？- 如果你有钱
-Tomorrow. -Then tomorrow you shall have the pages.
明天- 那你明天便能得到剧本
Oh, will you desist, madam!
停下来，女士！
- Oh! - Twenty pounds on delivery.
20英镑成交
Now, what is money to men like us?
钱财对我们何用？
Besides, if I need a play, I have another waiting-- a comedy by Shakespeare.
若我要剧码，还有莎士比亚的喜剧
Oh, Romeo.
罗密欧
- Gave it to Henslowe. - Never!
他已给汉斯乐了 - 不可能
Well, I'm to Deptford. I leave you my respects, Miss Rosaline.
我要去底佛市，再会，洛丝琳小姐
I gave Shakespeare two sovereigns for Romeo.
我付了定金给莎士比亚
You did, but Ned Alleyn and the Admiral's Men have the playing of it at the Rose.
但尼德和阿得曼剧组要在玫瑰剧院演出
Treachery!
背叛！
Traitor and thief!
小偷！叛徒！
Oh, no.
噢，不
No!
威廉·莎士比亚
By my head, here comes the Capulets.
以首起誓　卡布雷家族来了
By my heel, I care not.
以膝起誓　我可不以为意
Follow me close. I will speak with them.
紧跟着我　我跟他们谈谈
Gentlemen, good-den! A word with one of you.
先生们　日安　借步说话
Are you going to do it like that?
你要那样表演吗
Positions.
就位
- By my head, here comes the Capulets. - By my heel, I care not.
卡布雷家族来了　我可不以为意
Follow me close. I will speak to them.
紧跟着我　我跟他们谈谈
Gentlemen, good-den! A word with one of you.
先生们　借步说话
And but one word with one of us?
只是借步说话么
Couple it with something; make it a word and a blow.
言简意赅　一口气说完
Where's that thieving hack that can't keep his pen in his own ink pot?
那个不守本分的贼作家在哪？
What is this rabble?
这群暴民做什么？
Draw, if you be a man!
如果你是男人，拔剑！
Wonderful. Wonderful!
很好！很好！
And a dog.
还有条狗
No!
不
Have privy, players! Please!
求求你们　千万要小心
Oh! Not with my props!
别用我的道具呀
Oh!
Will! What-- - A writer's quarrel.
威廉　怎么... 　作家的口角
Quite normal.
十分常见
Stay here.
待在这里
You are hurt.
你受伤了
I dreamed last night of a shipwreck.
昨晚我梦见一场船难
- You were cast ashore in a far country. - Oh, not yet.
你被流放到远方　噢　还没
Not yet.
还没
'Ey, we need that for the balcony scene.
阳台的场景需要它
My investment! Lambert!
我的资金　蓝伯特
Vengeance!
复仇
A famous victory!
大胜利
Kegs and legs open, and on the house!
开酒庆贺　本店请客
Oh, what happy hour.
噢，快乐的时光
- This is a tavern! - It is also a tavern.
这是家酒馆- 也是家客栈
- I remember you. The poet! - Yes, William the Conqueror.
我记得你　那个诗人- 是的　征服者威廉
One at a time. One at a time.
一次一个　一次一个
Oh, he's a pretty one. Tell me your story while I tickle your fancy.
他很俊，在我挑逗你欲望时，告诉我你的故事
- It's a house of ill repute. - It is, Thomas, but of good reputation.
这是个堕落之地 －是的，但名声不错
Come. There's no harm in a drink.
来吧，一杯酒无伤大雅
You are welcome to my best house. Here's to the Admiral's Men.
欢迎莅临本店　敬阿得曼剧组
The Admiral's Men!
阿得曼剧组
Well, l-- I quite liked it.
嗯，我…我蛮喜欢的
Master Kent,
肯特阁下
you have not yet dipped your wick.
老二还没派上用场
My "wick"?
我的”老二”？
Mr. Fennyman, because you love the theater, you must have a part in my play.
你喜欢剧院，该在剧中有个角色
I am writing an apothecary, a small but vital role.
我在写一名药剂师，重要的小角色
My heavens. I thank you.
我的天　感谢你
What's the play about, then?
这剧码是描写什么？
Well, there's this nurse--
嗯，有个护士...
Silence, silence, silence!
安静！
Master Shakespeare...
莎士比亚阁下...
has asked me to play the part of the apothecary.
邀请我在剧中扮演药剂师
The apothecary?
药剂师？
What is this story? Where is the shipwreck?
这是什么故事？沉船在那里？
How does the comedy end?
这部喜剧怎么结局？
- By God, I wish I knew. - By God, if you do not, who does?
天哪，我希望我知道　- 你不知道谁知道？
Let us have pirates, clowns and a happy ending,
我们要海盗，小丑和一个喜剧牧场
or we shall send you back to Stratford to your wife.
或是送你回斯特拉福你老婆身边
Will! Mr. Henslowe! Gentlemen all!
威廉！汉斯乐！大家好！
A black day for us all! There is news from a tavern in Deptford.
多悲哀的一天！从迪佛酒馆传来消息
Marlowe is dead.
马罗死了
Stabbed.
被刺杀死的
Stabbed to death in a tavern at Deptford.
在迪佛酒馆被刺杀的
What have I done?
我真做了孽
He was the first man among us.
他是我们圈中的第一把交椅
A great light has gone out.
一颗巨星陨落了
Forgive me.
原谅我
God forgive me.
上帝原谅我
...Our Lord Jesus Christ's sake.
…奉耶稣基督之名
One morning in the month of May
“一个五月的早晨
From my cot I stray
“我开始迷惑
Just at the dawning of the day
“在黎明到来时
I met with a charming mai--
“我遇见迷人的仕女…”
You look sad, my lady. Let me take you riding.
小姐，你看来很悲伤，我们去骑马吧
- It's not my riding day, my lord. - Bless me, I thought it was a horse.
今天不是骑马日－你骑得不正是马吗？
I'm going to church.
我去教堂
Of course. I understand. It is to be expected.
当然，我明白，理所当然
Yes, it is to be expected... on Sunday.
对，若在星期天的话…
And on a day of mourning.
或是在凭吊的日子
I never met the fellow but once at your house.
我只在你家见过那家伙一次面
Mourning?
凭吊？
Who is dead, my lord?
谁去世了，阁下？
Oh! Dear God, I did not think it would be me to tell you.
天哪，想不到会是我告诉你
Great loss to playwriting and to dancing.
剧场及舞蹈界的一大损失
My lady.
小姐！
- He is dead? - Killed last night in a tavern.
他死了？- 昨晚在酒馆被杀
Come then. We'll say a prayer for his soul.
来吧，我们来为他祈祷
Who can remember sorrow
Spare me, dear ghost.
赦免我吧
Spare me, for the love of Christ. Spare me!
赦免我，奉基督之爱，赦免我！
Will!
威廉！
Oh, my love.
噢，我的爱
I thought you were dead.
我以为你死了
It is worse.
比死更惨
I've killed a man.
我杀了人
Marlowe's touch was in my Titus Andronicus,
马罗触发我写《泰特斯·安庄尼克斯》的灵感
and my Henry VI was a house built on his foundations.
“亨利六世”也是他打的基础
You never spoke so well of him.
你从未如此称赞过他
He was not dead before.
他以前还活着
I would exchange all my plays to come for all of his that will never come.
我愿用我的剧本来换他的
You lie.
你说谎
You lie by this river as you lied in my bed.
你一直在对我说谎
My love is no lie.
我的爱不是谎言
I have a wife, yes,
不错，我是有妻子
and I cannot marry the daughter of Sir Robert De Lesseps.
我也没法跟勒沙爵士的女儿结婚
You needed no wife come from Stratford to tell you that,
你不需人家的妻子从斯特拉福来告诉你
and yet, you let me come to your bed.
而且你又让我上你的床
Calf-love.
天真的爱
I loved the writer and gave up the prize for a sonnet.
我爱上了作者，却放弃了诗歌
I was the more deceived.
我完全蒙蔽了
Yes, you were deceived,
是的，你被蒙蔽了
for I did not know how much I loved you.
只因我不知有多爱你
I love you, Will,
我爱你，威廉
beyond poetry.
甚过诗歌
Oh, my love.
噢，我的爱
- You ran from me before. - When I thought you dead, I did not care...
你曾避开我－当我以为你死了，我不在乎…
about all the plays that would never come,
…你未写的剧本…
only that I would never see your face.
只在乎见不到你的面容
I saw our end, and it will come.
我见到终点，它一定会来
- You cannot marry Wessex. - If not you, why not Wessex?
- 你不能嫁给韦赛斯 －－如果不嫁你，为何不能嫁他？
If not Wessex, the queen will know the cause,
若不嫁给韦赛斯，女皇会知道原因的
- and there will be no more Will Shakespeare. - No. No.
那莎士比亚就不存在 －不
But I will go to Wessex as a widow from these vows,
我发誓会像寡妇一样去韦赛斯身边
as solemn as they are unsanctified.
虽然不圣洁但不失庄严
For killing Juliet's kinsman Tybalt,
因为杀了茱莉叶亲戚太伯特
the one who killed Romeo's friend Mercutio,
他杀了罗密欧的朋友马库修
Romeo is banished.
罗密欧被放逐
But the friar who married Romeo and Juliet-- - Is that me?
但证婚的修士…　- 是我吗？
You, Edward. The friar who married them gives Juliet a potion to drink.
你，爱德华，证婚的修士给茱莉叶一瓶毒药
It is a secret potion. It makes us seeming dead.
是个秘密药方，能使她看来像死去一般
She is placed in the tomb of the Capulets.
她会被放进卡布雷家的墓穴
She will awake to life and love when Romeo comes to her side again.
当罗密欧回来，她会醒在爱与生命中
I have not said all.
我还末说完
By maligned fate, the message goes astray which would tell Romeo of the friar's plan.
不幸地，修士的计划没有传到罗密欧耳中
He hears only that Juliet is dead.
他只听到茱莉叶的死讯
And thus he goes to the apothecary...
因此他去药剂师…
That's me.
是我
and buys a deadly poison.
...并买了致命的毒药
He enters the tomb to say farewell to Juliet who lies there cold as death.
他进入墓穴跟冰冷的茱莉叶诀别
He drinks the poison.
他喝下毒药
He dies by her side,
他死在她身在旁…
and then she wakes and sees him dead.
…当她醒来却见他死去
And so Juliet takes his dagger...
茱莉叶便拿起匕首…
and then kills herself.
…杀了自己
Well, that will have them rolling in the aisles.
好，那会让他们捧腹大笑
Sad... and wonderful.
悲伤…却精彩
I have a blue velvet cap that'll do well.
我有顶蓝色的帽子能派上场
I've seen just such a cap on an apothecary.
戴在药剂师头上应该不错
Just so.
刚好
Yes,
对…
it will serve.
…蛮适合的
But there's a scene missing.
但好像少了一幕
Between marriage and death?
在婚礼跟死亡中间吗？
The play...
这个剧本...
all written out for you.
...为你誊写下来了
I had the clerk at Bridewell do it.
找了布德维的书记誊写的
He has a good fist for lettering.
他写得一手好字
There is a new scene.
有新的一幕戏
- Will you read in for me? - "Wilt thou be gone? It's not yet near day.
你能读给我听吗？－“你会离开吗？白日还没来
It was the nightingale, and not the lark,
“不是百灵鸟，是夜莺
that pierced the fearful hollow of thine ear.
“美妙啼声穿透你耳中的空洞
Nightly she sings on yon pomegranate tree.
“夜晚在石榴树上啼唱
Believe me, love, it was the nightingale."
“相信我，吾爱，是夜莺
"lt was the lark, the herald of the morn;
“是百灵鸟，预告清晨来临
no nightingale.
“不是夜莺
Look, love, what envious streaks...
“看，吾爱，妒忌的光线...
do lace the severing clouds in yonder east.
“…把东逞片片云彩镶上边
Night's candles are burnt out,
“夜之烛燃尽了
and jocund day stands tiptoe...
“欢愉的日子蹑足站在...
on the misty mountaintops.
“…雾茫茫的山巅
I must be gone and live, or stay and die."
“我该离去存活；留下待死
"Yon light is not daylight; I know it, l.
“我知道，那不是道曙光
It is some meteor that the sun exhales...
“而是太阳散发的流星...
to be to thee this night a torchbearer...
“…今晚为你持着火炬...
to light thee on thy way to Mantua.
“…照亮通往满图的路
Therefore, stay yet.
“所以，留下吧
Thou needst not to be gone."
“你无须离去
"Let me be ta'en,
“来抓我吧
Iet me be put to death;
“让我受死吧
I am content, so thou wilt have it so.
“如果你满意，我也满足了
I have more care to stay...
“我宁愿留下…
than will to go.
“…不愿离去
Come, death, and welcome.
“来吧，死神，欢迎你
Juliet wills it so."
“茱莉叶心所向往”
You will go far, I fear.
我相信，你会成功
I hope we work together again.
希望我们再次合作
"Such mortal drugs I have, but Mantua's law...
“我有致命的药，但…
is death, death to any he that utters them."
“…私自出售会被依法处死”
Then him. Then me.
先他，再我
"Put-- Put this...
“这…
in any liquid thing you will and--" - Hah!
“…在任何你要的液体中…”
What is it? What is it? What is it?
怎么了？怎么了？
How silver sweet sound lovers' tongues by night.
夜晚爱人间的呢喃多么甜美
Like soft music-- - Shakespeare!
像轻柔的音乐…　- 莎士比亚
Upstart inky pup!
初出茅庐的冒失鬼
I'll show you your place, which is in hell!
我会让你下地狱
- You're on my ground now! - By God, I'll fight the lot of you!
你在我的地盘上!- 我跟你拚了
I am more than enough!
放马过来
Move!
让开
Absent friends.
我不能在场的朋友
This is the murderer of Kit Marlowe!
这是杀死马罗的凶手
Will?
I rejoiced in his death because I thought it was yours! That is all I know of Marlowe!
他死了我很高兴，我还以为是你
Will?
威廉？
Uh, it's true.
是真的
It was a... tavern brawl.
一场酒馆的争执
Marlowe attacked and got his own knife in the eye.
马罗出了手却误杀了自己
A quarrel about the bill.
因帐单而起的口角
The bill? Oh, vanity, vanity!
排名？噢，虚荣心作祟
Not the billing, the bill!
不是为排名，是帐单
Oh, God.
- I am free of it. - Where is she?
我自由了－她在哪？
Close it.
关起来
- My Lord Wessex. - The Rose harbors the ass that shits on my name!
玫瑰剧场庇护着使我蒙羞的笨蛋
Take it down stone by stone.
拆了它，片瓦不留
I want it plowed into the ground and sown with quicklime!
我要它夷为平地，寸草不生
Mr. Tilney, what is this?
提尔尼先生，这是什么？
Sedition and indecency.
反叛与不道德
Master of the Revels, sir. She's over here.
飨宴官大人，她在这里
- Where, boy? - There.
小孩，在那？　- 那里
I saw her bubbies.
我看见她的胸部
So, a woman on the stage!
噢，女人上舞台
A woman! I say this theater is closed!
女人！我命令这剧场关闭
Why, sir?
为什么？
For lewdness and unshamedfacedness!
因为淫荡和无耻
And for displaying a female on the public stage!
因为在公众舞台展示女人
Not him, her!
不是他，是她
That's who I meant.
我说的就是她
- He's a woman. - This theater is closed.
他是个女人 －此剧场关闭了
Notice will be posted!
会贴出公告
Ned, I swear, I knew nothing of this.
尼德，我发誓，我完全不知情
- Nobody knew. - He did.
没有任何人知道　- 他知道
I saw him kissing her bubbies.
我看到他吻她的胸部
It is over.
完了
I'm sorry, Mr. Henslowe.
汉斯乐先生，我很对不起
I wanted to be an actor.
我想成为一个演员
I'm so sorry, Will.
威廉，我真是非常抱歉
You were... w-w--
你是…
w-wonderful.
…真棒
Thank you.
谢谢
"Let me put this in any liquid thing you will and--"
“把这放进液体中，你会…”
Everything all right?
都好吗？
I would've been good.
我应该不错的
- I would've been great. - So would l.
我应该很棒的 - 我也是
We both would.
我俩都是
Lambert, kill him.
蓝伯特，杀他
That can wait.
这可以等
The Master of the Revels despises us all for vagrants and peddlers of bombast.
飨宴官瞧不起我们这些贩夫走卒的狂言大语
But my father, James Burbage,
但我的父亲，詹姆士·波贝
had the first license to make a company of players from Her Majesty,
是第一个领到开演员公司执照的
and he drew from poets the literature of the age.
他广撷当代诗人的作品
We must show them that we are men of parts.
我们要证明我们也能做到
Will Shakespeare has a play.
威廉·莎士比亚有剧本
I have a theater. The curtain is yours.
我有剧场，你可以自由使用
卡登剧场
由波贝先生同意修，费尼门制作
汉斯乐先生提供阿得曼剧组演出
罗密欧与茱莉叶的凄美悲剧
费尼门先生扮演药剂师在下午3：00钟
Will! We'll be needing a Romeo.
我们须要一个罗密欧
Oranges! Sweet oranges!
橘子！甜橘子
My ship is moored at bankside, bound for Virginia on the afternoon tide.
我的船停靠在岸边，等下午潮涨即驶向维吉尼亚
Please do not weep, Lady De Lesseps.
别哭
You are gaining a colony.
你得了个殖民地
And you, my lord, are gaining 5,000 pounds...
你阁下得了5000英镑
by these drafts in my hand.
…在我手中的这些汇票
Would you oblige me with 50 or so in gold...
请帮个忙先给50个左右的金币…
just to settle my accounts at the dockside?
…让让我付清在码头边的债务？
Ah, the bride!
新娘
Good morning, my lord.
早安，阁下
I see you are... open for business, so let's to church.
我见你开业了，让我们去教堂
Be gone!
走开
Hup, hup, hup!
凄美悲剧罗密欧与茱莉叶
Oh, my lord!
喔，阁下
- Be good to her, my lord. - I will.
请善待她，阁下 - 我会
Oh, God bless you!
愿神祝福你
Thank you. Uh, let go. There's a good nurse.
谢谢，让我走，那里有好奶妈
The tide will not wait!
涨潮是不会等的
Farewell! You'll all be welcome in Virginia!
再见！维吉尼亚欢迎你们
Candy apples!
糖衣苹果
Buy my apples!
买我的苹果
Thank you, sir. Apples!
Is this, uh-- Is this all right?
这样还可以吗？
Yeah.
Licentiousness is made a show! Vice is made a show!
淫荡的戏！邪恶的戏
Vanity and pride likewise made a show!
虚荣和骄傲也被搬上舞台
This is the very business of show!
这些全是戏的卖点
T-T--  Two
两…
T-T-T-T-- T-- T--
T-- T-T Two households--
两个世家…
- We're lost. - No, it will turn out well.
不妙了 －不，会好转
- How will it? - I don't know. It's a mystery.
如何好转？- 我不知道 上天知道
T-T-- T-- T T--
T-- T--
Two households,
两个世家
both alike in dignity,
势力相当
in fair Verona,
在优美的威洛纳
where we lay our scene.
是我们故事发生之地
From ancient grudge break to new mutiny,
从旧恨加新仇
where civil blood makes civil hands unclean.
历代的械斗使村民的手沾满血腥
From forth the fatal loins of these two foes...
从此就注定世代为仇…
a pair of star-crossed lovers take their life...
如流星相遇的一对爱侣殉情…
whose misadventured, piteous overthrows...
他们不幸的悲剧改变…
doth with their death bury their parents' strife.
由于他们的殉情埋葬了上一代的冲突
...the which of you with patient ears attend,
如果你能耐心听
what here shall miss, our toil shall strive to mend.
本剧将填补你刚才错过的情节
- Wonderful. - Was it...
很棒 －不是吗？
good?
好？
Gregory, on my word we'll not carry coals.
葛雷格瑞，发誓不再忍受侮辱
No, for then we should be colliers.
当然不，难道我们活该受辱？
I mean, and we be in choler we'll draw.
我是说，气到极便拔剑相向
- Master Shakespeare. - Luck be with you, Sam. Sam!
沙士比亚先生！－山姆，祝你好运
It's not my fault. I could do it yesterday.
不是我不对，我昨天还会
Do me a speech. Do me a line.
说一段话给我听，念段台词
"Parting is such sweet sorrow."
“离别是美丽的忧愁”
- Another little problem. - What do we do now?
还有个小问题 - 我们该怎么办？
The show must-- You know. - Go on!
这演出该…你知道　- 继续
Juliet does not come on for 20 pages. It will be all right.
茱莉叶要到20页后才上场，不会有问题的
- How will it? - I don't know. It's a mystery.
怎么办？－我不知道，上天知道
- Let them begin. - I will frown as I pass by.
让他们开始－我会对他们横眉立目
- Let them take it as they list! - Nay, as they dare.
让他们自己选择！－我料他们不会理睬
I will bite my thumb at them, which is disgrace to them if they bear it.
我会指着鼻子对他们挑衅，教他们难堪
Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?
你会吗？
- I do bite my thumb, sir. - Excuse me. Thank you.
先生，我会指着鼻子挑衅
- Thank you. Excuse me. - Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?
先生，你会指着鼻子挑衅吗？
- Can we talk? - Shh!
我们能谈谈吗？
- We have no Juliet. - No Juliet?
我们没有茱莉叶 - 没有茱莉叶？
- No Juliet? - It'll be all right, madam.
没有茱莉叶？－夫人，没事的
- What happened to Sam?
山姆呢？
- Who are you? - Thomas Kent.
你是谁？－汤玛士·肯特
Do you know it?
你会嘛？
- I serve as good a man as you. - Every word.
字字记得
Hyah! Yah!
I'll go along, no such sight to be shown,
我和你去，不是去找别的女孩
but to rejoice in splendor of mine own.
而是赞颂我洛丝琳了的美
Nurse!
奶娘
Where's my daughter? Call her forth to me.
我的女儿在那？　请帮我叫她
Now, by my maidenhead at 12 years old,
是我处女时代12岁时
I bade her come.
我叫她来
How now, who calls?
是谁在叫？
What, ladybird!
小瓢虫
God forbid! Where's this girl?
天啊！这女孩在那？
What, lamb!
绵羊
What, ladybird!
小瓢虫
What, Juliet!
茱莉叶
How now, who calls?
现在又是谁在叫？
- We'll all be put in the Clink. - See you in jail.
我们都要进牢了 - 在牢里见你
Your mother-- Your mother.
你的母亲…你的母亲
Madam, I am here. What is your will?
夫人我在此，你要什么？
This is the matter.
事情是这样
Nurse, give leave a while. We must talk in secret.
奶娘，请离席，我们要密谈
Nurse, come back again. I have remembered me; thou's hear our counsel.
奶娘，请回来，我想起来了，你来是要听我们的计划
Thou knowest my daughter's of a pretty age.
小女已是适婚年龄
- Faith, I know her age unto an hour. - She's not 14.
我甚至知道她的出生时刻　- 她不是14
Oh, I'll lay 14 of my teeth. And yet my teen be it spoken,
喔，可拿我14颗牙打赌，但都已坏了
I have but four--
我只剩下四…
Tell me, daughter Juliet,
告诉我，茱莉叶女儿啊
how stands your dispositions to be married?
你对结婚的看法如何？
It is an honor that I dream not of.
我做梦都没想到过
Hold, Tybalt! Good Mercutio!
住手！太伯特！马库修
I-- I'm sped.
我伤了
Courage, man; the hurt cannot be much.
勇敢些，兄弟：没那么严重
Ask for me tomorrow,
明天再问我
you shall find me a grave man.
你该替我找个挖坟人
Yes!
Yah!
"Such mortal drugs I have,
“我有致命的药
but Mantua's law is death to any he that utters them."
“但是任何人售此药会被满图的法律处死”
Then him. Then me.
先你，再我
Romeo, away, be gone!
罗密欧，走，快走
The citizens are up, and Tybalt slain. Stand not amazed!
人们聚拢来，太伯特被杀，别呆站着
The prince will doom thee death if thou art taken. Hence, be gone, away!
如果被逮住，王子会处死你，快跑
Oh, I am Fortune's fool!
噢，我被命运作弄
Why dost thou stay?
为何在此逗留？
Which way ran he that killed Mercutio?
那杀了马库修的人往那跑了？
That murderer, which way ran he?
那杀人犯往那跑了？
- There lies that Tybalt. - Up, sir. Go with me.
太伯特正躺在那儿　- 先生，跟我来
I charge thee in the Prince's name obey.
我奉王子的名命令你服从
Where are the vile beginners of this fray?
开始这场打斗的恶棍在那？
"Oh, I am Fortune's fool."
噢，我被命运作弄
You are married?
你已结了婚吗？
"lf you be married, my grave is like to be my wedding bed."
“如果你已结了婚，我的新婚床就像是我的坟墓”
Art thou gone so,
你已去了吗？
Iove, lord,
吾爱，吾主
aye, husband, friend?
吾夫，吾友？
I must hear from thee every day in the hour,
我时刻需要有你的消息
for in a minute there are many days.
因此度日如年
Oh, by this count I shall be much in years ere again...
噢，照此算来再见之时我已老矣…
I behold my Romeo.
…我的罗密欧
Farewell.
再见了
Oh, think'st thou we shall ever meet again?
噢，你想我们能再见面吗？
Methinks I see thee, now thou art so low,
我现在看你，你如此低下
as one dead in the bottom of a tomb.
如同坟底的死人
Either my eyesight fails, or thou look'st pale.
不是我的视力已退，就是你的脸色苍白
Then trust me, love,
相信我，爱人
in my eyes, so do you.
在我眼里，你也那么苍白
Dry sorrow drinks our blood.
忧愁使我们毫无血色
Adieu.
再见
Take thou this vial, being then in bed,
把这瓶拿去，当你在床上时
and this distilling liquor drink thou off.
喝了这瓶蒸馏的酒
No warmth, no breath, shall testify thou livest.
没有体温和呼吸，证明你的存在
And in this borrowed likeness of shrunk death...
你会在此一模拟的死亡中…
thou shalt continue two and forty hours,
有42小时之久
and then awake as from a pleasant sleep.
然后你会如同从甜睡中醒来
What ho! Apothecary!
哈罗！药剂师
Come hither, man. I see that thou art poor.
来这儿，我明白你是个可怜虫
Hold, there is 40 ducats.
拿着，这四十个金币
Let me have a dram of poison-- - Such mortal drugs I have,
让我拿这小瓶…　－马上生效毒药
but Mantua's law is death to any he that utters them.
但是满图的法律规定销售这东西的人都会受极刑
Art thou so-- - My poverty, but not my will, consents.
你是如此的…　－贫困会同意，但不是良知
I pay thy poverty and not thy will.
那我买通贫困，而不是良知
Eyes, look your last.
双眼，看最后一眼吧
Arms, take your last embrace.
手臂，做你最后一次的拥抱
And, lips,
和，你的唇
oh, you, the doors of breath,
噢，(你），这唇屏息入口
seal with a righteous kiss...
为香吻而密封…
the dateless bargain...
…这永恒交易…
to engrossing death.
…直到全然的死亡
Come, bitter conduct.
来吧，这令人痛苦的毒药
Come, unsavory guide.
来吧，呕心路程
Thou, desperate pilot, now at once...
你，这拚命三郎…
run on the dashing rocks thy seasick weary bark.
…我的倦体疲惫的身躯
Here's to my love!
这些给我心爱的人
Oh... true apothecary!
真正的药剂师
Thy drugs are quick.
药效很灵
Thus with a kiss...
拥吻…
I die.
…而去
Where is my lord?
我的主在那儿？
I do remember well where I should be, and there I am. Where is my Romeo?
我确实记得清楚，我在那里，我来了，但我的罗密欧在那？
Dead!
死了！
What's this?
这是什么？
A cup, closed in my true love's hand?
这瓶子，在我心爱人的手中？
Poison, I see,
毒药
hath been his timeless end.
心志未成而身先归去
Oh, happy dagger,
喔，一把刀
this is thy sheath.
我是把刀梢
There rest...
这儿安息…
and let me die.
…让我归去
A glooming peace this morning with it brings;
今早一片阴沉的宁静
the sun for sorrow will not show his head.
太阳也因着忧愁而不显脸
Go hence, to have more talk of these sad things.
走吧，我们会述说这些伤心事
Some shall be pardoned,
有些人会被赦免
and some punished;
有些人会被惩罚
for never was a story of more woe...
从没一个故事比…
than this of Juliet...
…茱莉叶和他的罗密欧…
and her Romeo.
…更愁苦
Bravo!
- Yea! Yea! - Yea!
- Bravo! - Yea! Bravo!
- God save the queen! - I arrest you in the name of Queen Elizabeth!
天佑吾主！－我以女皇之名逮捕你
Arrest who, Mr. Tilney?
逮捕谁呀，提尔尼先生
Everyone!
每一个人
Admiral's Men, the Chamberlain's Men...
阿得曼和张伯伦剧组的人…
and every one of you ne'er-do-wells that stand in contempt...
每一个惹麻烦而且藐视…
of the authority vested in me by Her Majesty!
…我这女王陛下授权的人
Contempt? You closed the Rose. I have not opened it.
藐视？你关了我的玫瑰剧场，我还没开张
That woman is a woman!
那扮女装的人是女的
What?
A woman? You mean that goat?
女人！你说那个丑女人？
I'll see you all in Clink, in the name of Her Majesty, Queen Elizabeth!
以伊莉沙白女王陛下之名，我们在监狱见
Mr. Tilney!
提尔尼先生
Have a care with my name. You will wear it out.
爱惜我的名声，不要滥用
The queen of England does not attend...
英国女王并不介入…
exhibitions of public lewdness.
淫荡的公共表演
So something is out of joint.
除非有些事真的脱离常规
Come here, Master Kent. Let me look at you.
肯特大师，过来这儿，让我看看你
Yes, the illusion is remarkable.
这幻觉真了不起
And your error, Mr. Tilney, is easily forgiven.
提尔尼先生，至于你的错，不去计较了
But I know something of a woman in a man's profession.
但是我了解一个女人在专属于男人的职业里
Yes, by God, I do know about that.
哦，老天，我真了解
That is enough from you, Master Kent.
肯特大师，这样够了
If only Lord Wessex were here.
如果韦赛斯公爵在场的话
He is, ma'am.
他在的
Y-Your Majesty.
女王陛下
There was a wager I remember...
我记得曾经有个赌注…
as to whether a play could show the very truth and nature of love.
…关于是否一出剧可以表现真纯之爱
I think you lost it today.
我想你今天是输了
You are an eager boy. Did you like the play?
你是个有热忱的孩子，你喜欢这个剧？
I liked it when she stabbed herself, Your Majesty.
我喜欢这剧当她刺伤她自己，女王陛下
Master Shakespeare.
莎士比亚大师
Next time you come to Greenwich, come as yourself,
下次到格林威治，以你真面目来
and we will speak some more.
我们可了多聊些
Your Majesty.
女王陛下
Why, Lord Wessex.
干吗，
Lost your wife so soon?
这么快就丢了老婆？
Indeed I am a bride short,
事实上是新娘失踪了
and my ship sails for the new world on the evening tide.
我的船今晚涨潮时要启程到新大陆
How is this to end?
怎么结局？
As stories must when love's denied--
当爱不存在了，故事…
with tears and a journey.
…只剩泪水和远走他乡
Those whom God has joined in marriage...
上苍钦证这个婚礼…
not even I can put asunder.
…甚至我都不能拆散
Master Kent.
肯特大师
Lord Wessex, as I foretold, has lost his wife in the playhouse.
韦赛斯阁下，如同我预测，在剧场失去了老婆
Go make your farewell and send her out.
去道别，送她出来
It's time to settle accounts.
该是解决债务的时候
- How much was that wager? - Fifty shillings.
赌注是多少？－五十先令
Pounds.
英镑
Give it to Master Kent. He will see it rightfully home.
拿给肯特大师，他会将钱平安送达
Tell Master Shakespeare something more cheerful next time...
告诉莎士比亚大师，下次写一些喜剧…
for Twelfth Night.
…第十二夜
Too late.
太迟了 太迟了
My Lady Wessex.
韦赛斯女士
A hired player no longer.
不必是演员了
Fifty pounds, Will,
威廉，五十英镑
for the poet of true love.
给真爱的诗人
I'm done with theater.
我不再写剧本了
The playhouse is for dreamers.
剧场是给做梦的人
Look what the dream brought us.
瞧，梦带来了什么
It was we ourselves did that.
那是我们自己完成的
And for my life to come, I would not have it otherwise.
在我未来的日子，我不愿有所不同
I have hurt you, and I'm sorry for it.
我伤害了你，我感到抱歉
If my hurt is to be that you write no more,
如果我的伤痛使你不再写作
then I shall be the sorrier.
我会感到更悲伤
The queen commands a comedy, Will,
女王命你写喜剧，威廉
for Twelfth Night.
第十二夜
A comedy.
一个喜剧
What would my hero be?
我的男主角会是怎样的？
The saddest wretch in all the kingdom, sick with love?
为爱而苦，至为悲伤的？
It's a beginning.
是一个开端
Let him be a duke, and your heroine--
让他是一个公爵，女主角－－
Sold in marriage and halfway to America.
美利坚之旅，无爱的婚姻
At sea, then.
在海上
A voyage to a new world.
驶向新世界
A storm. All are lost.
一场暴风，全都没了
She lands... on a...
她漂流到…
vast and empty shore.
…空旷的海边
She's brought to the duke--
她被带领到公爵那…
- Orsino.
…奥斯诺
- Orsino?
奥斯诺？
Good name.
好名字
But fearful of her virtue, she comes to him dressed as a boy.
惟恐失去贞洁，她装扮男孩去见他
And thus is unable to declare her love.
所以也不能倾诉她的爱意
But all ends well.
但结束还不错
How does it?
怎么结束？
I don't know.
我不知道
It's a mystery.
上天知道
You will never age for me,
在我心中你永远不会老
nor fade,
不会凋谢
nor die.
不会死亡
Nor you for me.
对我你也不会的
Good-bye, my love.
再见了，吾爱
A thousand times good-bye.
千次的再见
Write me well.
写信给我
第十二夜
My story starts at sea,
我的故事从海开始
a perilous voyage to an unknown land.
到个不知名地方的危险航行
A shipwreck.
船难
The wild waters roar and heave.
巨浪滔天
The brave vessel is dashed all to pieces,
大船被撞成支离破碎
and all the helpless souls within her...
船内无助的生灵…
drowned.
…淹没了
All save one:
只一个被救了
a lady...
一个女子…
whose soul is greater than the ocean,
…她灵魂比海更伟大…
and her spirit, stronger than the sea's embrace.
…而她的精神，比海更壮丽
Not for her a watery end,
她没被淹没…
but a new life beginning on a stranger shore.
…而在异地展开新的生活
It will be a love story,
那将是一个爱的故事…
for she will be my heroine for all time.
她将永远是我的女主角
And her name will be Viola.
她的名字叫薇奥拉
第一幕：海边